Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
Two years ago, I stood on the TED stage in Arusha, Tanzania.
قبل عامين وقفت في مسرح تيد في أروشا، تنزانيا.
I spoke very briefly about one of my proudest creations.
تحدثت بإيجاز عن أحد إختراعاتي التي تدعو للفخر.
It was a simple machine that changed my life.
لقد كانت آلة بسيطة غيّرت حياتي.
Before that time,
قبل ذلك الوقت
I had never been away from my home
لم أغادر بعيداً من منزلي
in Malawi.
في ملاوي.
I had never used a computer.
لم أستخدم كمبيوتر أبداً.
I had never seen an Internet.
لم أرى الإنترنت أبداً.
On the stage that day, I was so nervous.
على المسرح في ذلك اليوم، كنت متوتراً للغاية.
My English lost,
فقدت التعبير باللغة الإنجليزية،
I wanted to vomit.
كنت أرغب في التقيؤ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I had never been surrounded by so many azungu,
لم أكن محاطاً بالعديد من الناس "أزنقو"،
white people.
أناس بيض.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There was a story I wouldn't tell you then.
كانت هناك قصة لم أرويها حينئذ.
But well, I'm feeling good right now.
لكن حسناً، أشعر بتحسن الآن.
I would like to share that story today.
أريد أن أتقاسم معكم تلك القصة اليوم.
We have seven children in my family.
لدينا سبعة أطفال في أسرتنا.
All sisters, excepting me.
كلهم بنات، بإستثنائي.
This is me with my dad when I was a little boy.
هذا أنا مع أبي عندما كنت طفلاً صغيراً
Before I discovered the wonders of science,
قبل أن أكتشف عجائب العلم،
I was just a simple farmer
لقد كنت فلاحاً بسيطاً
in a country of poor farmers.
في بلد لفلاحين فقراء.
Like everyone else, we grew maize.
مثل أي شخص آخر، نزرع الذرة.
One year our fortune turned very bad.
في عام من الاعوام أصبحنا فقراء جداً.
In 2001 we experienced an awful famine.
عام 2001 شهدنا مجاعة فظيعة.
Within five months all Malawians began to starve to death.
خلال خمسة أشهر بدأ كل الملاويين التضور جوعاً حد الموت.
My family ate one meal per day, at night.
أكلت أسرتي وجبة واحدة يومياً، في الليل.
Only three swallows of nsima for each one of us.
فقط ثلاث لقمات من نسيمة (وجبة) لكل واحد منا.
The food passes through our bodies.
يمر الغذاء عبر أجسادنا.
We drop down to nothing.
وصلنا لحد اللا شئ.
In Malawi, the secondary school,
في ملاوي، اليوم الثاني للمدرسة،
you have to pay school fees.
يجب أن ندفع مصاريف الدراسة.
Because of the hunger, I was forced to drop out of school.
بسبب الجوع، أضطررت لترك المدرسة.
I looked at my father
لقد فكرت في والدي،
and looked at those dry fields.
وفكرت في تلك الحقول الجافة.
It was the future I couldn't accept.
كان ذلك المستقبل الذي رفضت قبوله.
I felt very happy to be at the secondary school,
شعرت أنني سعيد جداً في اليوم الثاني للمدرسة.
so I was determined to do anything possible
لذا كنت مصمماً على فعل أي شئ ممكن
to receive education.
لأتلقى تعليمي.
So I went to a library.
لذا ذهبت الى المكتبة.
I read books, science books, especially physics.
قرأت كتب، كتب علوم، خصوصاً الفيزياء.
I couldn't read English that well.
لم أستطيع فهم الإنجليزية لتلك الدرجة.
I used diagrams and pictures
أستخدمت المخططات والصور
to learn the words around them.
لأتعلم الكلمات القريبة منها.
Another book put that knowledge in my hands.
كتاب آخر وضع تلك المعرفة بين يدي.
It said a windmill could pump water and generate electricity.
ذكر أن الطاحونة يمكن أن تضخ مياة وتولد الكهرباء.
Pump water meant irrigation,
ضخ المياة يعني الري.
a defense against hunger,
دفاع ضد الجوع،
which we were experiencing by that time.
الذي كنا نعاني منه في ذلك الوقت.
So I decided I would build one windmill for myself.
لذا قررت أن أبني طاحونة واحدة لنفسي.
But I didn't have materials to use,
لكن لم تتوفر لي المواد لأستخدمها.
so I went to a scrap yard
لذا ذهبت الى ساحة للخردة
where I found my materials.
حيث وجدت المواد اللازمة لي.
Many people, including my mother,
العديد من الناس، ضمنهم والدتي،
said I was crazy.
قالوا أنني مجنون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I found a tractor fan,
وجدت مروحة حاصدة،
shock absorber, PVC pipes.
ممتص صدمات، مواسير بلاستيكية.
Using a bicycle frame
بإستخدام إطار دراجة
and an old bicycle dynamo,
ومحرك دراجة قديم،
I built my machine.
بنيت آلتي.
It was one light at first.
لقد كانت خطاً واحداً في البداية.
And then four lights,
وبعد ذلك أربعة خطوط،
with switches, and even a circuit breaker,
مع مفاتيح ، وحتى محول الدائرة،
modeled after an electric bell.
على غرار فاتورة الكهرباء.
Another machine pumps water
آلة أخرى تضخ الماء
for irrigation.
لأغراض الري.
Queues of people start lining up at my house
صفوف الناس بدأت في الإنتظام عند بيتي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
to charge their mobile phone.
لشحن هواتفهم المحمولة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I could not get rid of them.
لم أستطيع التخلص منهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the reporters came too,
وجاء صحفي أيضاً،
which lead to bloggers
الذي قاد الى المدونات
and which lead to a call from something called TED.
والذي قاد لإتصال من شئ يسمى تيد.
I had never seen an airplane before.
لم أرى طائرة بتاتاً من قبل.
I had never slept in a hotel.
لم أخلد الى النوم في فندق.
So, on stage that day in Arusha,
لذا، على المسرح في ذلك اليوم في أروشا،
my English lost,
فقدت لغتي الإنجليزية،
I said something like,
قلت شيئاً مثل،
"I tried. And I made it."
"لقد حاولت، ولقد نجحت."
So I would like to say something
لذا ارغب في قول شئ
to all the people out there like me
لكل الناس هناك، مثلي
to the Africans, and the poor
الى الأفارقة، والفقراء
who are struggling with your dreams.
الذين يناضلون من أجل أحلامهم،
God bless.
بارك الله فيكم.
Maybe one day you will watch this on the Internet.
ربما ستشاهدون هذا يوماً ما على الإنترنت.
I say to you, trust yourself and believe.
أقول لكم، ثقوا بأنفسكم وآمنوا.
Whatever happens, don't give up.
مهما يحدث لا تستسلموا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)